Good morning today is the 10th of March
no
it
is the 12th of אדר *Adar*.
It's ערב arev, שבת *Erev Shabbos*. We're going into פרשת זכור *Parshas
Zachor*. One of the only situations when you can have שבת זכור
*Shabbos Zachor* after תענית אסתר *Ta'anis Esther* is when the fast gets
pushed off to Thursday, pushed early to Thursday.
What does it say? Wasn't it...
Well
it's מוקדם *mukdam*,
but there's a whole question of פורענותא לא מקדמינן *puranuta lo makdiminan*,
right? And it's not פורענותא *puranuta*.
You think goes to that ראב"ד *Ravad*'s opinion and it's not פורענות
*puranut*.
Right, and the ראב"ד *Ravad* and the מאירי *Meiri*. Okay, so today's
דף *daf* we're going to be doing מ"ו *Mem Vav*. Pick up...
no we did מ"ו *Mem Vav* yesterday, picking up from the bottom
of מ"ו *Mem Vav*, the second to last line. Well really we'll
go back to the סימן *siman*, very timely סימן *siman*, עמלק סימן
*Amalek siman*.
Some of the אחרונים *acharonim* on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* get interested
in like why why did חז"ל *Chazal* דווקא *davka* pick these four
cases with a סימן *siman* that's עמלק *Amalek*.
But it's easy to remember.
Easy to remember, of course, you have to remember עמלק *Amalek*, but
we also have to
we're not supposed to make such a big deal about
reminding... we're supposed to be תמחה זכר עמלק *timche zecher Amalek*. So
it's all a paradox there. Okay, עמלק סימן *Amalek siman*. תנו רבנן
Tano rabbanan: *Tano rabbanan*, ערב arev, מעיד me'id ללווה והוא דאית ליה
ארעא אחריתי *areiv meid l'loveh v'hu d'is leh ara'a achriti*. So the
ערב arev *areiv*, we discussed this I think already a little bit
yesterday, an ערב arev *areiv*, a cosigner on a loan. Now why
anyone would ever actually agree to be a cosigner on a loan
is a separate question.
Bankers refer to them as fools with pens.
Yes, fools with pens. And we'll get to them, it's basically like
the last סוגיא sugya. *sugya* in בבא בתרא Bava Batra. *Bava Basra*,
so we'll be there in a few months.
All the ערב arev *areiv* discussion. Right,
parents often do it for children. But in a business arrangement, why
would you, you know,
any microeconomics assumes that everyone acts logically, right?
Maybe not business, microeconomics, you're trying to help out a friend.
You're trying to help out a friend and it may be a
form of צדקה *tzedakah* too if someone needs a loan, so being
an ערב arev. *areiv* on a loan to help someone get a
loan is also a way of giving צדקה *tzedakah* as well. So,
תנו רבנן *Tano rabbanan*, ערב arev מעיד ללווה *areiv meid l'loveh*. The
ערב arev, *areiv* is not considered to be נוגע בדבר nogea badavar,
*nogeia badavar* to the extent that it compromises his ability to testify
on behalf of the לווה *loveh* that the property belongs to the
לווה *loveh*. You might think, oh the ערב arev? *areiv*, because if
the לווה *loveh* doesn't have any properties, they're going to extract liens
on his properties and that would be a problem for him, so
he's not really נוגע בדבר nogea badavar *nogeia badavar* if the לווה
*loveh* has other properties והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי *v'hu d'is leh
ara'a achriti*. Because if the לווה *loveh* has other properties, they're not
going to so soon come after the ערב arev *areiv*'s properties.
Is it against that opinion that says you can
go to the ערב arev *areiv*? Ah, we're going to get to
that, that's the קבלן Kablan, *kablan* case, that's the ק' *kuf* of
the עמלק *Amalek*. So this is ע' *ayin*. So מ' *mem*, מלווה
malveh מעיד ללווה והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי *malveh meid l'loveh v'hu
d'is leh ara'a achriti*. The מלווה malveh *malveh* himself could testify about
the לווה *loveh* והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי *v'hu d'is leh ara'a
achriti*. In a similar case, as long as the לווה *loveh* has
other properties, it's not going to compromise the ability of the מלווה
malveh *malveh* to be able to collect the debt.
So in such a case, the מלווה malveh *malveh* is not so
נוגע בדבר *nogeia badavar* either. Even though the מלווה *malveh* actually has
a closer relationship even than the לווה *loveh*, he stands to gain
quite a bit from that situation, but because the לווה *loveh* has
other properties, his ability to testify about this specific property is not
going to give him any specific benefit.
Yeah, but what's not brought into here is like a בעל חוב
ba'al chov *ba'al chov* is going to be מבינונית *mi'beinonit*, right? Let's
say... Right, that comes up in the next סוגיא sugya. *sugya*. Let's
say this guy has all these זיבורית ziburis *ziburit* and
now the stuff that you're מעיד *meid* on would be בינונית beinonis
*beinonit*. That's exactly what the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* quotes that on top
of מ"ז עמוד א' *Mem Zayin amud aleph*. We'll get to that
in just a sec. Okay, so לוקח ראשון מעיד ללוקח שני והוא
דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי *loka'ach rishon meid l'loka'ach sheini v'hu d'is leh
ara'a achriti*. What if someone sold their property and they sold this
field first and then they sold another field later? So the rule
is that in terms of collecting liens on properties that even when
you have a שטר shtar. *shtar* you could collect the debt from
a property, even real estate, even real estate that was sold after
the time the loan was taken. So in this case,
the לוקח *loka'ach*, you go by whoever was sold to most recently.
So the לוקח שני *loka'ach sheini* will be presumably taken from first.
So the לוקח ראשון *loka'ach rishon* can testify that the field belongs
to the לוקח שני *loka'ach sheini* even though he stands to benefit
because he's sort of putting someone else up as a human shield
for him in terms of, he's putting the לוקח שני *loka'ach sheini*
up to be collected from first, even if he testifies that it
belongs to him, because והוא דאית ליה ארעא אחריתי *v'hu d'is leh
ara'a achriti*. As long as that לוקח שני *loka'ach sheini* has other
properties, there's no fear in the mind of the לוקח ראשון *loka'ach
rishon* that testifying about this particular field is going to enhance his
own ability to retain the property that he purchased. Now again, in
that kind of situation, if you get collected from, you can go
back and claim back the purchase price from the original seller, but
at that point... if he's defaulted on his loan he may not
have the money to pay.
Okay. Now we're up to קוף, קבלן, Kablan, right on top of
מ''ז ע''א, Mem Zayin Amud Aleph, קבלן, Kablan this is not a
normal קבלן Kablan, that is like a laborer, this is as the
רשב''ם Rashbam says קבלן ערב קבלן, Kablan arev Kablan, a special kind
of ערב, arev a special kind of cosigner who has agreed that
actually this is even dammer than a regular ערב, arev that you
can normally with the ערב areiv, agreement is that if the לוה
loveh defaults on the loan then the מלווה can go collect from
the ערב areiv second. The קבלן ערב Kablan arev is actually you
could go collect from him immediately. The question is how does that
work? We're going to see the גמרא Gemara has a difference of
opinion. קבלן, Kablan אמרי לה מעיד, amrei lah me'id, there are those
who say that he could testify cause he's not considered נוגע בדבר,
ואמרי לה אינו מעיד ve'amrei lah eino me'id and there are those
who say that he cannot. So this was what Micah was saying,
so you look in the רשב''ם Rashbam אמרי לה אינו מעיד amrei
lah eino me'id and the first of the narrow lines because it's
talking about in the case of those who say that he cannot
testify say that it's because he's נוגע בעדות, nogea b'eidus, why? Because
in that case suppose that the לוה loveh has a certain properties,
like for example the לוה loveh has a זיבורית ziburis field and
a בינונית beinonis field. And if the so in the case where
you could collect from the ערב immediately
then because the בעל חוב ba'al chov can only collect from בינונית
beinonis field, medium grade field, then if the לוה loveh doesn't have
any בינונית beinonis field left, if he only has a זיבורית field
which is the low quality cropland then the בעל חוב ba'al chov
will be sort of forced to go to the ערב. So by
suggesting or by being able to testify on behalf of the לוה
loveh that this property belongs to him the ערב is increasing his
chances of not being collected from. That's why that opinion is אמרי
לה אינו מעיד. amrei lah eino me'id.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמרי לה מעיד, amrei lah me'id, those
who say that he could testify, כערב דמי, k'arev dami, whatever it's
the same as a regular ערב, the extent to which he gets
הנאה hana'ah from this arrangement by being able to testify is rather
minimal and so we still wouldn't consider him נוגע בעדות nogea b'eidus
to the extent that he would be worried he would be lying.
But why is it minimal, meaning isn't it, it's
the same as a regular ערב? The regular ערב we already said
was...
what I'm trying to say, what I'm trying to understand is a
regular ערב you still go to the
לוה loveh first. But in our קבלן Kablan case can't you go
to him right away? You could.
But the benefit, so the benefit that he stands to gain by
testifying that the לוה loveh that this is the לוה's loveh property
is very minimal.
Basically it's the same as, meaning because he could go to him
first anyway so then what does he gain?
Right. But certainly even more so. So for the opinion that says
מעיד then he's actually even better off and the opinion that
says אינו מעיד eino me'id it's because he's worse off. So it's
how you think about that relationship. The fact that you could go
to the ערב first but does that mean that he's then less
concerned about the לוה's loveh properties and therefore he's less נוגע בדבר
or does that actually mean that now he wants to make it
more attractive that the מלווה will collect from the לוה loveh directly
and not from him?
Yeah, like to avoid that he's gonna come to me right away.
Right. So the מחלוקת machlokes here is fundamentally do you then see
that relationship as fundamentally in favor of the ערב or in favor
of the לוה loveh in that way, like how does he see
his relationship to those properties?
So they're sort of both right in a sense, you could see
it in different perspectives. אמרי לה אינו מעיד דניחא ליה דהוי בידיה
amrei lah eino me'id d'nicha leh d'havi beyadei because he prefers that
it be in the control of the לוה loveh so that the
לוה loveh looks like a more attractive person to go to to
collect from the loan. Okay. תרווייהו דכי אתי בעל חוב, tarvayhu d'ki
atei ba'al chov, for both of them when the בעל חוב comes
so מה דבעי שקיל, mai d'baei shakil, he could take whatever he
wants because that's what it means to be the קבלן ערב. Kablan
arev. There is a little bit of a difference of opinion between
the רי''ף מגאש Ri Megash and רשב''ם Rashbam about how to understand
what that קבלן Kablan relationship really is.
But in all four of these cases is someone is testifying that
the לוה loveh is the debtor has properties that can be collected
from? Correct. So what's, so who said otherwise?
Who,
there's some other מערער mearer is coming to say no it's my
property.
Ah, so it's a case in which there needs to be testimony
to the fact that the לוה's loveh got lands that are liened
that could be used to pay off...
Correct. Suppose it's a land, a piece of land he doesn't have
a חזקה chazakah on but he claims
or it's
a contested field of some kind, so he doesn't have חזקה, chazakah,
he needs witnesses, something like that, right.
And these four guys?
Right, well the last one, the קבלן Kablan, is a מחלוקת, machlokes,
right.
So I just want to make sure on the קבלן, Kablan I
can go get the קבלן's Kablan land if I think the קבלן's
kablan land is better than the,
not that it's better, that he has available בינונית beinonis, field? בינונית,
yeah.
So I might like his land rather than the debtor's?
Well that's why he shouldn't get himself into these kind of situations.
It's, it's interesting. actually far and for...
Right. So that's exactly the question. Is—is the מחלוקת machlokes between the
רי מגאש Ri Migash and and the רשב"ם Rashbam is how did
this relationship get started? Is it that the קבלן kablan. went and
borrowed money from the מלווה and then lent it to the לוה,
loveh, just like a two-stage loan? Well, in that case, he's just
a מלווה to this לוה. loveh. That's the relationship. But the alternative
is to say, no, actually, he went and negotiated it as an
ערב, but he took on those terms of of being the ערב
that you would be able to collect from him first. That sort
of different ways of seeing that relationship. And there's a lot more
to get into obviously with all these things and compare it to
the סוגיות sugyos we've seen in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia.
What's the bottom line difference in terms of action though?
There's no—no, they agree about the case. They agree about—they're just disagreeing
about how you define the קבלן. And obviously it has ramifications for
how to treat other cases and how to see that relationship and
what—what motivates those positions. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rebbi Yochanan, Rebbi
Yochanan says: אומן אין לו חזקה בן אומן יש לו חזקה. uman
ein lo chazakah, ben uman yesh lo chazakah. So the משנה Mishnah
had said that a craftsman, presumably if I take my shoes to
the shoemaker and drop them off, the shoemaker doesn't have any חזקה
chazakah of ownership over shoes because we can assume that a shoemaker
who has shoes is because he's fixing them for somebody else. Right,
that was the whole previous סוגיא. sugya. Right. And that was in
our משנה Mishnah and the previous סוגיא. So רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
says אומן אין לו חזקה. uman ein lo chazakah. The craftsman himself
does not have the חזקה chazakah on those objects. בן אומן יש
לו חזקה. Ben uman yesh lo chazakah. But the son,
presumably has—the father drops dead one day, לא עלינו חס ושלום. lo
aleinu chas v'shalom. But in that case, the son will inherit the
properties. He has a whole bunch of shoes in the house, but
he's not a shoemaker. Or alternatively, some years later, someone comes and
say, hey, those are my shoes or that's my motorcycle or whatever.
And he says, no, just 'cause my father was a motorcycle repairman
means I can't have a motorcycle?
So wait, is there a second case where the אומן uman is
still alive?
No, at that point, that's—it
seems like in both cases he's dead.
Wait, so it means the בן אומן יש לו חזקה ben uman
yesh lo chazakah is only if the אומן uman is dead?
Right. בן אומן—it Ben uman doesn't say that. So we're going to
see. The גמרא Gemara is going to explain first
because you just give it to a son and his son can
now automatically get rid of any ownership issues and say this is
a חזקה.
chazakah. Correct. The גמרא Gemara is going to continue and explain a
little bit more 'cause he has to obviously it has to just
not just be חזקה, chazakah, but has to be חזקה שיש עמה
טענה. chazakah sheyesh imah ta'anah. He has to be able to make
a claim. So what is he going to say? And אריס אין
לו חזקה. aris ein lo chazakah. A sharecropper does not have a
חזקה chazakah because we know that he's a sharecropper, so he's just
working on somebody else's land. בן אריס יש לו חזקה. Ben aris
yesh lo chazakah. But if a the son of the sharecropper who
himself is not a sharecropper, then he does have the חזקה. chazakah.
But if he was a sharecropper, he would not have the חזקה.
chazakah.
Correct.
Except with the אריס, aris, it's only he doesn't have the חזקה
chazakah on the land that he's been hired to be a sharecropper.
Correct, right.
There're going to be limitations for all of these. It's not a
general principle.
So the בן אריס ben aris has חזקה chazakah on the land
that their
father—not actually, he could get a חזקה. chazakah. Meaning if after my
father was a sharecropper on this land, then I later am able
to be living on that land for three years and no—no מחאה,
mecha'ah, then I'll be able to have חזקה chazakah from that. But
if the אריס aris himself was working on that land for three
years, it doesn't count 'cause everyone knows that he had it as
an אריס. aris.
He has to be living on the land subsequent to his father's
demise for three years, or he's been—he lived his whole life on
the land, now he's twelve—he's fifteen years old, his father...
Presumably the second one. That is, as long as he's himself not
an אריס, aris, he can create a חזקה. chazakah. Okay. גזלן ובן
גזלן. Gazlan u'ven gazlan. But a thief and the son of a
thief, neither of them have חזקה. chazakah. אין להם חזקה. Ein lahem
chazakah. But בן בנו של גזלן, ben b'no shel gazlan, a grandson
of a גזלן, gazlan, יש לו חזקה, yesh lo chazakah, does have
a חזקה. chazakah. So now we'll have to see.
So why—but this בן גזלן ben gazlan is not a thief himself
either.
Presumably, right. But we would have a greater assumption that the בן
גזלן ben gazlan is going to have a worse טענה ta'anah or
a false טענה ta'anah than a בן אריס ben aris or a
בן אומן. ben uman. We're going to see.
So are we talking about like inheriting things?
Yeah, we are talking presumably about inheriting the land. So let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara. asks: היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What is
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan talking about?
אי דאתו בטענתא דאבוהון, Ei d'asu b'ta'anta d'avuhon, if they just come
with the same claim as their fathers, that is
the—the בן אומן ben uman says my father got this pair of
shoes to work on them as a pair of shoes. Well, obviously,
right? אפילו הנך נמי לא, afilu hanach nami lo, then none of
them should have a חזקה chazakah because if they just come with
the same claim, just it was my father who did it instead
of myself, so then obviously it's not a חזקה. chazakah. אי דלא
אתו בטענתא דאבוהון, Ei d'lo asu b'ta'anta d'avuhon, and if they don't
come with their father's claim,
אפילו בן
גזלן נמי.
afilu ben
gazlan nami. That is—meaning what? Meaning what's the father's claim? The father's
claim is: I stole it, or I'm an אריס, aris, or I'm
an אומן, uman, right?
A גזלן's gazlan's never going to claim it's mine because I stole
it.
His claim is:
you actually gave it to me, you sold it to me.
Okay.
But like
the cloak or whatever that you gave me to repair.
You're saying the אומן. uman. And even— And the אומן, uman, even
if he makes a claim you sold it to me, we don't
trust him, but more or less.
But it doesn't, what if he says oh this was like a
cloak that someone gave to repair but they actually gave it
as my property? Right.
Right. Or something. Right. Okay.
I think it may be a bit of a מחלוקת ראשונים machloket
rishonim actually about what טענת דאבוהון ta'anat d'avuhon means here, whether it
means
the normal claim like you sold it to me or it was
my father's or anything like that or compared to is it claiming
it based that it was gotten in that way. So אפילו בן
גזלן נמי. afilu ben gazlan nami.
Wait, who's on the side? The רשב"ם Rashbam says that אבינו הוריש
לנו. avinu horish lanu. Right, he doesn't say how, right?
Right, so we don't have necessarily enough, I mean the רשב"ם Rashbam
I would have to take a closer look at some of these
רשב"מים. Rashbams.
Anyway, so, so the point is though that so if you would
say that it's that they came without their father's טענה, taina, then
even the בן גזלן ben gazlan should also be believed, right? אפילו
בן גזלן נמי. afilu ben gazlan nami. So צריכא, tzericha, דקאמרי עדים
בפנינו הודה לו. d'ka'amri edim be-fanenu hodeh lo. So no, there are
witnesses who say that בפנינו, be-fanenu, in front of us, הודה לו,
hodeh lo, that he admitted to him. That is what, that the
original owner admitted to the father of these people that it belongs
to him. So what happened? Like we have to, right, we have
the אב, av, we have the בן, ben, we have the מרא
קמא. mara kamma.
So the מרא קמא mara kamma told the father that it belongs
to him in front of witnesses. And now the son has inherited
it. That's what we're describing. In that case...
Wait, the
מרא קמא mara kamma he admitted.
There was a הודאה, hoda'ah, הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים. hoda'at ba'al
din ke-mea edim.
Why is there a difference in the גזלן gazlan then?
Ah, why is there a difference in the גזלן? gazlan? So now
we're going to see. So why should even in such a case
the בן גזלן ben gazlan does not have a חזקה? chazakah? So
let's take a look. Okay, ומאף על גב ד, u-ma'afal gav de,
okay, דקאמרי עדים בפנינו הודה לו, d'ka'amri edim be-fanenu hodeh lo, הנך
איכא למימר קושטא, hanach ika le-meimar kushta,
for these we assume that it was truthful, קאמרי, kamre, האי אף
על גב דאודי נמי לא מהימן. hai afal gav d'odei nami lo
meheman.
But for the case of a גזלן, gazlan, even if he had
admitted, we're going to assume that he's not telling the truth. כדרב
כהנא, ki-d'Rav Kahana, just like what רב כהנא Rav Kahana said, דאמר
רב כהנא, d'amar Rav Kahana, אי לאו דאודי ליה הוי ממטי ליה
ולחמריה לשחוור. i lav d'odei leh havei mamti leh u-lechmariya le-shachvar.
If you would not have admitted to me, the גזלן gazlan says,
right? The father is a גזלן. gazlan. So he says to the
מרא קמא, mara kamma, if you don't admit to me that it's
rightfully mine in front of these witnesses, then I'm just going to
go turn it over to somebody else. I'm going to go turn
it over to the some other thief or to the some other
to the government or something. So the because he's a גזלן, gazlan,
he's a strongman, he's able to manipulate the system and he can
get a coerced הודאה.
hoda'ah. Oh, he's going to extort you.
Exactly. And שחוור shachvar means? שחוור, shachvar,
it sounds like is based on the תרגום targum of of the
word for a thief. That's what רשב"ם Rashbam quotes from where it
says the רשב"ם Rashbam says במדבר ט"ז be-midbar tet zayin in the
medium wide lines, he quotes כדמתרגמינן, ke-d'metargeminan, לא חמור אחד מהם נשאתי,
lo chamor echad mehem nasati, ולא חמרא דחד מנהון שחרית. ve-lo chamra
de-chad minhon shachrit.
I did not steal the donkey of one of yours. So it's
some kind of an expression, but more or less to I'll give
it over to another thief. Like that's kind of his his threat.
So אמר רבא. amar Rava.
So here they translate שחוור shachvar as requisitioner.
A requisitioner? I don't know what requisitioner. To requisition something.
It
sounds
like an official title and the
root in this context of שין חית ריש shin chet resh is
force labor performed for the government.
Okay, so
it's like he's threatening to say he'll give it over to the
to public domain kind of thing. Okay. אמר רבא, amar Rava, פעמים
שאפילו בן בנו של גזלן נמי אין לו חזקה. pe'amim she'afilu ben
beno shel gazlan nami ein lo chazakah.
There are even times where the grandson of a גזלן gazlan will
also not have a חזקה. chazakah. Why? היכי דמי? heichi dami? Which
case? כגון דאתי בטענתא דאבא דאבוהון. ke-gon d'ati be-ta'anta d'aba d'abuhon.
So maybe he comes with the the claim of his grandfather, that
is we in a case where the father had predeceased the grandfather
so he would inherit directly from the grandfather perhaps, or even if
he just makes the claim that oh you sold it to my
grandfather but everyone knows that the grandfather is a גזלן. gazlan. So
in that case, היכי דמי גזלן? heichi dami gazlan? So what kind
of גזלן gazlan are we talking about? That's a bigger question. אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, כגון שהוחזק על שדה זו בגזלנותא. ke-gon
she-huchzak al sadeh zu be-gazlanuta.
Everybody knows that he's living on this land even for many years,
but that he stole it. That's the kind of גזלן. gazlan. ורב
חסדא אמר ve-Rav Chisda amar כגון דבי פלוני שהורגין נפשות על עסקי
ממון. ke-gon de-bei ploni she-horgin nefashot al iskei mamon. רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says
it's like a mafia family. People, a whole family of known people
who all are, you know, willing to kill people over monetary issues.
So the issue there, the רשב"ם explains, is the difference whether we
would say that this גזלן gazlan only has a חזקה chazakah problem
about this field, because that's the field for which he's known to
have stolen it, or is he understood to be a גזלן gazlan
for many fields? Right. So that's the question between רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan thinks this
גזלן... gazlan... is a גזלן gazlan who stole one field, so he
could make a חזקה chazakah on any other field, just not this
field.
נפקא מינא Nafka mina between the שיטות. shittot. Right.
And רב חסדא Rav Chisda thinks it means this person is disqualified
in general. Another interesting- yes.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda lived in בבל. Bavel. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
lived in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Maybe things were worse in בבל
Bavel and the Jews were engaged in organized crime?
I don't know enough about any of those things to know the
history of it or anything like that.
So the טור Tur in קמט Kuf Mem Tet in discussing all
this, I mean the טור Tur קמט Kuf Mem Tet is very
long, but the טור Tur quotes a יש אומרים, Yesh Omrim, which
I could not track down who it was, that if the גזלן
gazlan does תשובה teshuvah and then like it's known, it's a דבר
ידוע davar yadua that he did תשובה גמורה, teshuvah gemurah, then at
that point, you would trust even the גזלן. gazlan. That he says-
right something like that. So they did תשובה?
teshuvah? Yeah, they're clean.
No, but even the גזלן gazlan himself, if the person is a
thief and has rehabilitated himself to the extent that he's known to
have done תשובה, teshuvah, according to that יש אומרים, Yesh Omrim, he
would be believed and the טור Tur says I don't like it.
This goes into some of Rabbi Linzer's תורה Torah about sort of
how at what point does a community feel obligated or mandated to
actually
treat someone as if they have done תשובה. teshuvah. Even there's one
thing to have done תשובה teshuvah between you and God, there's another
thing for the community to actually trust you again. And those are
important questions to think about.
So if he stole the field, does תשובה, teshuvah, he has to
return the field.
No, no, no, meaning, not the same field. At some point later,
they say to him "Oh, do you have a חזקה chazakah on
this field?" So he would be believed to say "Yeah, I returned
it and then I eventually bought it from him" or something like
that. That's the argument.
Okay.
So in the רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan case, where he says היכי
דמי גזלן כגון דאוחזק לאהו שדה זו
בגזלנותא,
heicha dami gazlan kegon de'uchzak le'ahu
sadei zu begazlanuta, so then
why would anyone if there's- if everyone's talking about this field, why
would the בן בנו ben beno be believed?
Because a בן בנו ben beno could still try to say "Yeah,
my grandfather stole it 50 years ago, but then I went and
bought it from you or my father bought it from you" or
whatever, you know.
But I mean if he's changing the time- so the- so the
בן ben of a גזלן gazlan is not believed to say that
"I went and bought it"?
The son of the גזלן gazlan is not believed to say that,
correct. Because that's our principle is that generally because his claim has
to be- because a claim has to be going back to "Oh,
my father bought it from you" or something like that, then he-
he doesn't have legs to stand on to make a claim on
his own, right.
No, I understand, but the claim was that "my father bought it
from you". It makes no difference
if the- if the- there's a גזלן gazlan and then the next
generation if he says "my father bought it from you" he's not
believed because the guy was a גזלן. gazlan. If the בן בנו
ben beno says the same thing... No, but- בן בנו ben beno
is the point.
Correct. That's exactly the point.
But if the בן ben of the גזלן gazlan said "I bought
it from you", he would be believed, wouldn't he? Or not?
No, because he'd tend to bring a שטר.
shtar, So why would the בן בנו ben beno of the גזלן
gazlan be believed?
בן בנו ben beno is believed because he can put it onto
his father. The בן גזלן... ben gazlan... What do you mean put
it on? Meaning he can claim "my father bought it from you".
But if the בן גזלן, ben gazlan, if the בן גזלן ben
gazlan tries to make a טענה, ta'ana, he- we don't trust him.
Because if he says "I bought it"...
I think it's because we assume he's like inherited some of the
like...
It- part of it is-
it's- it says it's the father told- that the son of the
robber told the grandson
that it was his grandfather's. Then- then he wouldn't have it.
But
if he didn't tell him, if he just passed it down, right,
the kid just assumes a father bought it and then right.
Even though this is the same field people been talking about for
the past 50 years as a stolen field.
Yeah, but the son says "Yeah, my father- it's not a- mean,
again, how מוחזק בגזלנותא muchzak begazlanuta like what does that mean? Just
because it has a rumor going around doesn't mean the rumor is
true, you know, all those kind of questions. Okay. Anyway. תנו רבנן:
אומן אין לו חזקה. Uman ein lo chazakah. So an אומן uman
we know from the משנה Mishnah doesn't have a חזקה chazakah right
in the properties, but
ירד מאומנתו, yarad me'umnato, if he quits the business, יש לו חזקה,
yesh lo chazakah, then he could create a חזקה. chazakah.
Meaning on anything later or on things earlier?
Presumably on things later. The claim of the חזקה chazakah has to
go from after that.
Okay. So אריס אין לו חזקה, aris ein lo chazakah, ירד מאריסותו,
yarad me'arisuto, יש לו חזקה, yesh lo chazakah, a similar rule for
the אריס. aris. If the אריס aris was while he's an אריס,
aris, he has no חזקה chazakah but once he quits, then he
can create a חזקה. chazakah. בן שחלק, ben shechalak, what about a
child, an adult child who no longer lives at home, has has
left the house? This goes into that question of גדול הסומך על
שלחן אביו נקרא קטן gadol hasomech al shulchan aviv nikra katan if
you're still dependent on your parents in some ways you're still considered
to be a קטן. katan. So this is a child who's left
home and is financially independent. ואשה שנתגרשה ve'isha shenitgarsha or a divorced
woman, הרי הן כשאר כל אדם, harei hen keshar kol adam, they
have financial independence, so their claims of חזקה chazakah could be treated
independently from the from the parents or from the previous the ex-husband.
Okay, בשלמא בן שחלק, bishlama ben shechalak, so I understand בן שחלק...
ben shechalak... I understand why you would tell me this about a
בן שחלק. ben shechalak. איצטריך סלקא דעתך אמינא אחולי אחיל גביה. itzt'rich
salka daitach amina acholi achal gabei. So
maybe you'll just think even an adult child the parents will forgive
everything. That is what, that the children could make a חזקה chazakah
on property that the parents previously owned. If the son is living
on their, on their parents' field for three years, you might think,
oh they'll always be מוחל. mochel. So it's not a good חזקה,
chazakah, it's just that they actually granted ownership. And we say no,
קמשמע לן דלא. kamashmalan d'lo. That is that if a financially independent
child is living on a field for three years and there's no
מחיאה, mecha'ah, we must trust that the חזקה chazakah worked actually to
create it as their own and don't think that it means that
it was actually the parents' field. Yeah.
Just sorry, are you recording YouTube right now?
No, the YouTube I couldn't log into the computer.
Use the sound looked like it was working yesterday.
Yeah, I missed it
though.
My sound is also not working very well.
Okay.
So change the batteries.
Yeah, I've changed the batteries. Exactly. Okay, אלא אישה שנתגרשה. ela ishah
shenitgarshah. What about a woman who is divorced? פשיטא. pshita. It's so
obvious. What do you mean? A woman who's divorced wouldn't be able
to make a her own חזקה chazakah even on a field that
the husband, right? Imagine this. The ex-husband owns one field and then
the divorced wife is living there for three years. You think he's
not going to protest? Right? So פשיטא. pshita. So לא צריכה. lo
tzricha. It must be that we need it במגורשת ואינה מגורשת. bim'gureshah
v'eina m'gureshah. A case of ספק safek divorce. If you remember back
to מסכת גיטין, Masechet Gittin, all sorts of cases. He threw the
גט get to her and it landed halfway in between and it
and then the dog ate the גט get or something. So we
don't know. All this kind of things. So there are all these
ספק safek cases and in a case of במגורשת ואינה מגורשת, bim'gureshah
v'eina m'gureshah, the husband still has a financial responsibility to support her
until they get a kosher גט. get. וכדרבי זירא דאמר רבי זירא
אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר שמואל כל מקום שאמרו חכמים מגורשת
ואינה מגורשת בעל חייב במזונותיה. uk'deRabbi Zeira d'amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi
Yirmiyah bar Abba amar Shmuel kol makom she'amru chachamim m'gureshah v'eina m'gureshah
ba'al chayav bimzonoteha. So according to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, quoting from
שמואל, Shmuel, in a case where there's a ספק safek divorce, the
husband is still financially responsible to support the wife even afterwards. And
therefore we would think, we might think, if the wife tries to
get a חזקה chazakah on the husband's property, now imagine three years
after they were ספק safek divorced and he still hasn't given her
a גט, get, that's a pretty bad situation as well. But just
imagine the situation. So you might think, oh, he's not protesting because
he's still financially connected to her and that's why there's no מחיאה.
mecha'ah. So קמשמע לן, kamashmalan, that's the whole point of this מימרא
memra to teach us that actually in such a case the woman
even if she's only ספק safek divorced, would still be able to
make a חזקה chazakah on properties that were owned by her husband
slash ex-husband.
So in that case we're going to choose to see her or
emphasize the מגורשת m'gureshah status? Right. What's a מימרא? memra?
It's a statement of the אמוראים. Amora'im.
Or a statement in the גמרא.
Okay.
בעל חייב במזונותיה. ba'al chayav bimzonoteha. אמר רב נחמן אמר לי הונא.
amar Rav Nachman
amar li Huna. So רב נחמן Rav Nachman quotes from רב הונא.
Rav Huna. כולן שהביאו ראיה ראייתן ראיה. kulan she'hevi'u re'ayah re'ayatan re'ayah.
If any of these people actually brought proof like witnesses or a
שטר, shtar, then it works, meaning even the בן אריס ben aris
and the בן אומן ben uman and even an אומן uman and
all kinds of people. Okay. ומעמידין שדה בידן. u'ma'amidin sadeh b'yadan. And
we can treat the field as belonging to them. However, גזלן שהביא
ראיה, gazlan she'hevi re'ayah, if the גזלן gazlan brings proof, the גזלן
gazlan himself, אין ראייתו ראיה. ein re'ayato re'ayah. If he brings witnesses
because we assume the גזלן gazlan is just strong-arming them into doing
it.
Yes? Wait, can I go back for just a second? Sure. Is
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah in a way, is
in a way he's חולק cholek on the previous, in other words,
במגורשת ואינה מגורשת. bim'gureshah v'eina m'gureshah.
So by
the aspect
she's not מגורשת.
m'gureshah. Correct. But for the aspect of חזקה chazakah she is מגורשת.
m'gureshah.
And that's why רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan needed to teach us that
she could make a
חזקה chazakah because normally because she's חייב במזונותיה. chayav bimzonoteha.
Even though he's obligated to support her, right. Even though he's obligated
to support her financially, we still understand that legally she has the
ability to create an independent חזקה chazakah of ownership even on a
property that belonged to her husband.
Oh, that's the חידוש chidush of I see. I got it.
Right. Okay. And obviously in cases like this you imagine complex divorce
situation with a complex financial situation. I'm sure the emotions are running
very high.
So you need this clarification.
You need a lot of clarification. You need good rabbis and you
need people to stay calm and it's very hard.
And there are
יש אומרים yesh omrim would say
that this is only a גזלן gazlan that has not done
תשובה. teshuvah.
Presumably yes, exactly. Correct. Because it's like, look, I have a שטר,
shtar right, or anything. So anyway, so אין ein and ואין מעמידין
שדה בידו. v'ein ma'amidin sadeh b'yado. Even if a גזלן gazlan brings
your שטר Shtar, or brings witnesses or whatever because he's a גזלן,
gazlan, we're not going to believe him and we don't trust his
proof. For this?
For this field, correct.
Well, it depends on the previous סוגיא. רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right. So מאי קא משמע לן, mai kamashmalan, what
does he come to teach? So תנינא לקח מסיקריקון וחזר ולקח מבעל
הבית. tanina lakach misikrikon v'chazar v'lakach miba'al habayit. What if you now
going back to... our favorite סיקריקון Sikrikon from מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin.
So the סיקריקון Sikrikon is some kind of a bandit who goes
and steals people's property, right, and then he sells them. So, what
if you bought a field from the סיקריקון Sikrikon and then you
really wanted this field? So you bought it from the סיקריקון Sikrikon
and you bought it from the original owner. חזר ולקח מבעל הבית.
Chazar ve-lakach mi-baal ha-bayit. מקח הוא בטל. Mekach hu batel. Then your
purchase is cancelled. That is presumably what? Presumably that we're talking about
the purchase from the
סיקריקון. Sikrikon. You would be able to get the money back. Obviously
from getting back from the סיקריקון Sikrikon would be a bit complicated,
but the רשב״ם Rashbam has a lot to say about this and
the whole question of how much fear the סיקריקון Sikrikon imposes on
the relationship becomes complicated.
So you're saying מקח הוא בטל Mekach hu batel even from the
בעל הבית?
Baal ha-bayit? From the בעל הבית, Baal ha-bayit, that's
what the רשב״ם Rashbam says? No, I'm just asking you, presumably I
mean the סיקריקון? Sikrikon? But why?
I already bought the... ah, okay, right, right, you're right. Meaning even
if you buy it from the בעל הבית, Baal ha-bayit, he's only
selling it to you because you already bought it from the סיקריקון
Sikrikon and it was lost to him and he has some kind
of יאוש, Ye'ush, but really it's his field and he wants it
back and right, right, right. So מקח
הוא בטל. Mekach hu batel. But the רשב״ם Rashbam says גזלן נכרי
הורג על עסקי...
Gazlan nochri horeg al iskei... Right. Of course he's a נכרי. Nochri.
We don't want to suggest that it would be a Jewish סיקריקון.
Sikrikon. Oh okay, it could be. Okay. So and we're now getting
into the question of coerced sales. So this is one of the
core סוגיות Sugyot in בבא בתרא. So let's... לאפוקי מדרב. L'apukei mi-de-Rav.
This comes to contradict רב's Rav opinion. דאמר רב, De-amar Rav, לא
שנו אלא דאמר ליה Lo shanu ela de-amar leh לך חזק וקני.
Lech chazek u-knei. So it only works if you actually tell someone,
that is to go make a חזקה, Chazakah, if someone tells you,
yeah, go and go and acquire this field and get a חזקה.
Chazakah. אבל בשטר קנה. Aval bi-shtar kanah. So
if
you purchased it by שטר, Shtar, that is in the case of
if you bought it from the... right, that's if the בעל הבית
Baal ha-bayit sold you the סיקריקון Sikrikon field by telling you to
go do a קנין חזקה, Kinyan chazakah, build a wall, knock down
the wall, lock the door, all kinds of things like that, dig
a hole. That would be one thing, because that's where sort of
he's less invested in the process.
Okay, but when he tells you to do that, then what?
Then the מקח הוא בטל. Mekach hu batel. However, if בשטר קנה
קמשמע לן כדשמואל. Bi-shtar kanah kamashma lan ke-di-Shmuel. So then if you
purchased it sold it by a שטר, Shtar, in such a case
the מקח Mekach would not be בטל. Batel. That comes to teach
us like שמואל Shmuel said. דאמר כדשמואל דאמר, De-amar ke-di-Shmuel de-amar, אף
בשטר נמי לא קנה. Af bi-shtar nami lo kanah. So but שמואל's
Shmuel opinion is that no, even if by a שטר, Shtar, we
don't consider it as a good sale. עד שיכתוב אחריות נכסים. Ad
she-yichtov achrayut nechasim. Until you include the אחריות הנכסים, Achrayut ha-nechasim, that
is the ability for the liens on the property to be extracted
from the field. Okay, because that's...
Yeah, at some point I would be... it would be helpful if
you laid out the facts of this case.
The facts is סיקריקון Sikrikon stole a field from ראובן. Reuven. Okay.
סיקריקון Sikrikon sold the field to שמעון. Shimon. Okay. Now שמעון Shimon
goes and buys the field from ראובן Reuven also. So he bought
it twice. He really wanted to own it.
He bought it from the mafioso
and from the original owner.
And the סיקריקון Sikrikon had stolen it from ראובן. Reuven.
Correct. So now the question is, well is that a good sale?
Maybe ראובן Reuven only sold it because he didn't really have control
over it anymore. So in the case where he said go... if
ראובן Reuven told שמעון, Shimon, yeah, go and purchase the field by
making a חזקה Chazakah on the field, that is what it says
that מקח הוא בטל Mekach hu batel according to רב's Rav opinion.
And רב Rav would say if he sold it by a שטר,
Shtar. then it would be a good sale.
If ראובן Reuven sold it to שמעון Shimon for the... if ראובן
Reuven sold it in the second sale, the question is, in other
words, in the second sale when ראובן Reuven then sells it to
שמעון, Shimon, because he wants the... the question is whether that's a
good sale or not without a שטר. Shtar Right.
Okay. So if this was by חזקה... Chazakah... and the reason why
it might not ever be a good sale is because maybe ראובן,
Reuven, he would really love to just keep his property. But he's
out money because it was stolen the first time. He's been extorted
to sell it for a really low price. He'll at least take
the money and get on with his life. Right.
So if he sells it by a שטר Shtar though, רב Rav
says it's good and שמואל Shmuel says it's not good.
Right. In other words, if עד כדי כך Ad kedei kach he
actually writes a שטר Shtar to שמעון Shimon and we have no
reason to think that שמעון Shimon was extorting ראובן, Reuven, but
שמעון Shimon
sees that he's muscling in on a vulnerability to get this field.
Right.
And that's why especially if he sells it to him by חזקה,
Chazakah, it's kind of like he's throwing up his hands, but he's
not really agreeing to it.
And that's... yeah, it's complicated.
It is a little bit complicated. Okay. אבל בשטר קנה קמשמע לן
כדשמואל דאמר אף בשטר נמי לא קנה עד שיכתוב אחריות נכסים. Aval
bi-shtar kanah kamashma lan ke-di-Shmuel de-amar af bi-shtar nami lo kanah ad
she-yichtov achrayut nechasim. So שמואל Shmuel says that if with a שטר
Shtar you're not
קונה Koneh until the שטר shtar actually has a full a full
liability. ורב ביבי מסיים בה משמיה דרב נחמן. Ve-Rav Bibi mesayem bah
mi-shmei de-Rav Nachman. And רב ביבי Rav Bibi elaborated on this quoting
from רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, later than רב Rav
and שמואל, Shmuel, that everyone agrees that if he sold it בשטר.
bi-shtar.
איני eini or whoever it was
that
this תנינא Tanina doesn't say that? Correct. It always seems to say
מכר בטל, mecher batel, really means that
מכר בטל mecher batel unless it was with a שטר shtar according
to רב, Rav, or it was a שטר shtar that had אחריות
נכסים achrayus nechasim according to שמואל. Shmuel.
Well, how does the אחריות נכסים achrayus nechasim help?
It enhances, it just means that the level of commitment...
well, it would be a higher price,
right?
The level, no, that the level of commitment in terms of the
sale is higher because he's saying now that I sold it to
you, I've even transferred over the liability of people coming to
have liens against
me, against me
and this and this specific field. Obviously, ראובן, Reuven, why would he
do that unless he really means to give it to him? Right.
Meaning, he's giving up the ability for the... if someone had a
loan on him to be able to... right, and he could have,
right normally, if it was a מלוה בשטר, milveh b'shtar, he could
collect from the field even after he had sold it to שמעון.
Shimon. If he sells it באחריות נכסים, b'achrayus nechasim, it means he's
covered, he's taking off the...
right. No, שמעון, Shimon, that would be a greater reason to show
that ראובן Reuven wants שמעון Shimon to have it.
We're worried about ראובן. Reuven.
Yes, yes, yes, it's the price הנאה hana'ah for ראובן. Reuven. Right,
why would he do that to his disadvantage? It's to ראובן's Reuven
advantage to sell it that way.
No, it's to שמעון's Shimon advantage, which demonstrates that ראובן Reuven is
more willing, that he's actually willing to sell it.
It means ראובן Reuven
makes someone else benefit on it.
Right, it's beneficial to שמעון Shimon that the people who have debts
on ראובן Reuven cannot collect it from שמעון's Shimon field. That's what
אחריות נכסים achrayus nechasim means. If someone, if ראובן Reuven owes somebody
else money, then they come to שמעון Shimon who just bought this
field to... sorry, he sold it with אחריות נכסים, achrayus nechasim, I'm
safe. That proves that ראובן Reuven really wanted to sell it.
Why does that prove he really wanted to sell... why would he
do that? If I'm a seller... oh, oh, oh, I get that.
I want as little obligation as possible. Right, okay, שטר is better.
Yeah,
what's the question?
Okay, and I'll still do it just to your benefit, שמעון. Shimon.
שמעון Shimon owned the field, right?
No, ראובן Reuven owned the field, originally.
ראובן Reuven is original owner. סיקריקון Sikrikon stole it from ראובן. Reuven.
סיקריקון Sikrikon sold it to שמעון. Shimon.
Then שמעון Shimon
went and bought it again from ראובן. Reuven.
So he paid twice?
He paid twice. He really wants this field.
He wants ראובן Reuven to come and say you're on stolen property.
Right, correct.
He is. The question is why did ראובן Reuven sell it to
שמעון? Shimon? Is it just because he feels powerless and he's trying
to make the best of a bad situation, or did he actually
want to sell it to שמעון? Shimon?
But okay, so the extortionist stole it from ראובן, Reuven, right? Yes.
So then what does ראובן Reuven have to sell to שמעון Shimon
if it's stole if the...
he has the actual ownership of the land.
Even though he's not on it anymore?
He's not on it
anymore, right.
He was concerned that שמעון Shimon is just making a veneer for
something he's really stolen and's trying to like you know clean up
his reputation and it's really stolen and he really doesn't deserve to
be there, or he's trying to be a מענטש. mentsch. Whatever it
is, but it doesn't make a difference, end of the day, end
of the day, like you know, he didn't really have to sell
it.
But I have one more question. Why is the extortionist going to
give over this land?
Because he wants to make money off of it, that's the whole
point of his business.
No,
שמעון...
Shimon... סיקריקון Sikrikon steals it from ראובן Reuven and then sells it
to שמעון Shimon to make a lot of profit.
He doesn't go and buy it from the extortionist, שמעון Shimon doesn't
want people walking around and saying he built his empire on stolen
property. Right, he wants to make good to ראובן. Reuven.
Right, okay,
so רב ביבי Rav Bibi came along and clarified a little bit
more detail.
רב ביבי מסיים בה משמיה דרב נחמן קרקע אין לו אבל מעות
יש לו. Rav Bibi mesayeim bah mishmei d'Rav Nachman karka ein lo
aval maos yesh lo. That is, all of this applies in a
case of קרקע, karka, but if it was מעות maos that was
being transferred, then he does have the rights to it. אבל אמרו
עדים בפנינו הודה לו לא.
aval amru eidin bifaneinu hodo
lo lo. If the witnesses say in front of that, in front
of us, that he admitted to it, that is what? That the
witnesses in this case, what we're talking about, we're talking about the
who gets to claim the money back from
the sale, right? Okay. דמעות יש לו כגון שאמרו עדים בפנינו מנה
לו הגזלן לנגזל ונתן לו המעות או ש
d'maos yesh lo k'gon she'amru eidin bifaneinu
mana lo ha-gazlan l'nigzal v'nasan lo ha-maos o she- so that's the
case going back now, we're thinking about the גזלן gazlan case, right,
that's what we saw previously. That the גזלן gazlan can have a
חזקה chazakah or the בן גזלן ben gazlan can have a חזקה
chazakah in a case where the witnesses say בפנינו הודה לו, bifaneinu
hodo lo, that the original owner admitted to the גזלן gazlan that
it belonged to him, right? So we said, oh, so he's clarifying.
What are we talking about? So קרקע אין לו אבל מעות יש
לו. karka ein lo aval maos yesh lo. He doesn't get the
rights to the field, that is a גזלן gazlan cannot establish a
חזקה chazakah on a field, but he could get paid for it,
meaning if he sold it to someone else or something like that.
You could get the money back, he could get the money back,
right, because if he admitted to him that it's his in front
of witnesses, even though we don't trust the... witnesses necessarily, but he
could get the money back. So מנה לו. maneh lo. אבל אמרו
aval amru so מנה לו. maneh lo. אבל אמרו עדים בפנינו הודה
לו. aval amru edim befaneinu hodo lo. Right,
what did the witnesses say? Did the witnesses say בפנינו מנה לו?
befaneinu maneh lo? The witnesses said, "it's a hundred dollars for him
in front of us," or אבל אמרו עדים בפנינו הודה לו? aval
amru edim befaneinu hodo lo? He just admitted to him however much.
Meaning what? Meaning that in a case of a loan, not in
a case of a transfer of a field like we said before
about the witnesses admitting the original owner. Now what are we talking
about? Witnesses to a loan or to a gift of some kind
and he said, "oh, I admit that I owe you a hundred
dollars." The witnesses say בפנינו הודה לו, befaneinu hodo lo, סתם stam
without any monetary amount, it doesn't work because it's non-descript.
But if it was he admitted to a hundred dollars in front
of him, then it does work.
Wait, how are you getting the money in front of them?
That's the מנה לו. maneh lo.
מנה לו maneh lo what? That he admitted שאמרו עדים בפנינו מנה
לו, sheamru edim befaneinu maneh lo, he gave the money. Okay, okay.
So like they're saying, yeah, he actually, right?
He started counting out money.
Now I'm saying, yeah, I paid money for that, right?
Right, right.
It might be a verb, מנה לו.
manah lo. מנה לו, manah lo, he counted out the money for
him, instead of a noun, not a noun.
Right, yeah, maybe you're right.
Are we saying that the robber probably paid the full market value?
The robber didn't pay any money.
How'd we say that?
The robber stole it from—that's what makes him a robber.
He stole it from ראובן. Reuven. Right. And then he sold it
to שמעון. Shimon.
He sold it, okay,
to make money.
That's what we're debating here is whether he gets that money back.
No, now we're talking about a different case.
Anyway, we're learning from a different case to this case. It's a
little bit tricky. These are hard סוגיות sugyot sometimes. Okay. רב כהנא
Rav Kahana that אמר: amar: So אי לאו דאודי ליה, ei lav
deodei leh, if he hadn't admitted to him, right, הוה מיטמינא ליה
ודידיה וחמרא לשחפר. hava mitamina leh vedidei vechamra leshachpar. So it's the
same threat. He can always just say, like the גזלן gazlan guy
is going to say, if you don't admit to me, right, he
can pressure you and say, if you don't admit that it's mine,
I'll just turn it over to the authorities. ואמר רב הונא veamar
Rav Huna and now a new set of סוגיות. sugyot. So but
these are all connected to the same kind of thing. אמר רב
הונא: amar Rav Huna: תליוהו וזבין זביניה זבינא. talyuhu vezavin zivinei zivina.
If they hung him up, presumably they threatened him in some way,
וזבין vezavin to sell something, זביניה זבינא, zivinei zivina, then his sale
is a good sale.
That is, if you sell something under pressure, under coercion, it's still
a good sale. מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the reason? כל דמזבין
איניש אי לאו דאניס לא הוה מזבין. kol demazbin inish ei lav
deanis lo hava mazbin.
You would never sell—certainly לא תחמוד lo tachmod by doing that?
In other words—certainly לא תחמוד.
lo tachmod. Yeah. Good sale, but you're still—right. Coercion. Right.
So you would never sell anything,
excuse me, you would never sell anything if you didn't have some
kind of external pressure, some kind of אונס. ones. It's better to,
in the
Talmudic mindset, it's always better to own things than it is to
own money. So things, you would never sell a thing, particularly real
estate, unless you had some external pressure.
I don't get that at all.
כל דמזבין איניש, kol demazbin inish, any person selling something, אי לאו
דאניס לא הוה מזבין, ei lav deanis lo hava mazbin, you would
not sell.
I'm in בבל, Bavel, I want to make עליה, aliyah, I'm going
to sell my property in בבל Bavel and go buy property in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Good, so that's a—that's an אונס. ones. That counts for this sense
as a kind of an external pressure that's
putting—it's better to have stuff.
The fact that you're selling something indicates that there's some external pressure
against you. Whether it's real אונס ones like someone holding a gun
to your head or whether it's market pressure or whether it's your
personal desires.
Right, right. Somehow our gut feeling tells us, right, there's a sale
at this store and I'm going to go buy it, or you
know, I can get a really good price, the market on oranges
is really high and my warehouse is full of oranges so I'm
going to sell all my oranges. That makes sense. So that's part
of this question. But what do they mean by that? Right, to
the extent that there is some external pressure that forces you to
sell. That's the idea.
Correct, correct. Okay. ודילמא שאני אונסא דנפשיה מאונסא דאחריני? vedilma shani onsa
denafshei meonsa deachrinei?
Maybe there's a difference between your life is in danger or a
financial אונס ones or some other kind of pressure on you. אלא
כי דתניא. ela keditanya. It's like this ברייתא. braita.
So יקריב אותו yakriv oso from ויקרא פרק א, Vayikra Perek Aleph,
the fact that to bring a קרבן, korban, in this case talking
about I think it's about קרבן
חטאת—no,
korban
chatat it's קרבן עולה. korban ola. יקריב אותו, yakriv oso, מלמד שכופין
אותו, melamed shekofin oso,
the בית דין Beis Din can force you to bring the קרבן.
korban. יכול בעל כרחו? yachol baal korcho? Could it really be against
your will though? Meaning what do you mean force you? תלמוד לומר
לרצונו, talmud lomar lirtzono,
the פסוק pasuk says it has to be לרצונו, lirtzono, you have
to agree to it. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? What case is that?
כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. kofin oso ad sheyomar rotzeh ani.
They force him until he says, "I want to." you agree to
it. That is, in some sense, there is a certain understanding of
what coercion is, but coercion to the extent that you actually prefer
it. So how do we see coercion? So okay, ודילמא שאני התם
דניחא ליה דהוי ליה כפרה, v’dilma shani hatam d’nicha leh d’havei leh
kappara,
maybe it's because we fundamentally assume that a person wants כפרה kappara
for their sins? So even if they're being forced against their will
to bring this sacrifice by the בית דין, Beit Din, it's really
to their benefit. אלא מסיפא, Ella meseifa, so what about the סיפא
seifa of the same ברייתא? braita? וכן אתה אומר בגיטי נשים, v’chein
ata omer begitei nashim, is the same principle applies in a case
of divorce, כופין אותו עד שיאמר רוצה אני. kofin oto ad sheyomar
rotzeh ani. The בית דין Beit Din can force the husband to
give a גט. get. What? That's
not a thing? אין אונס בגיטין? ein ones begitten? No, no. אין
אונס בגיטין ein ones begitten is about if you didn't show up
on time and there was a תנאי tnai and all those kind
of things from the beginning of כתובות Ketubot and things like that.
That’s not a general statement?
That’s not right. So in general, the גט get has to be
given with the full consent of the husband. But in this case,
if the בית דין Beit Din has determined that he needs to
be forced to divorce his wife, then the בית דין Beit Din
can force him until he says that he wants to, and that’s
not considered to be coercive, that’s considered to be willing.
Okay, yeah, just we have one more line. ודילמא שאני התם, v’dilma
shani hatam, maybe that’s different, דמצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים. demitzvah lishmoa divrei
chachamim.
Maybe that's different because those are cases where the בית דין Beit
Din is forcing you and that's a rabbinic injunction that you have
to listen to the rabbis. אלא סברא הוא אגב אונסיה גמר ומקני.
Ella sevara hu agav onseih gamar umakni.
So it’s a basic assumption that even though you’re being forced, you
still in the state of being forced, you’ll still end up deciding
that you’re going to agree. Okay.
David?
You have a question?
I have a question on this whole concept of a forced sale.
Yeah. Are we assuming that if it was forced, the person who
was doing the forcing paid the preferred amount, or at least the
market value?
Maybe they paid a little bit less, but presumably the idea is
the person didn’t want to sell it, being pressured to sell it,
not being stolen from but being coerced. As Michael pointed out, it’s
a separate prohibition לא תגזול lo tigzol and לא תגנובו lo tignovu
compared to the prohibition of לא תחמוד. lo tachmod. לא תחמוד lo
tachmod in the Ten Commandments basically means don't pressure people into selling
things to you that you want them to sell to you that
they don't want to sell. That’s a lot of what this is
about, is that same kind of coercive situation.
Isn't there a
distinction that maybe they're saying here and I'm just not hearing it?